WILL FAUGHT

Sacramento, California • jobs@willfaught.com github.com/willfaught • linkedin.com/in/willfaught

Summary

Software engineer with 9+ years of professional experience and undergraduate and graduate degrees in Computer Science who has built software and infrastructure to scale. Pursuing back-end and infrastructure roles at senior and higher levels, as well as lead and management roles. Looking for ownership of interesting, important projects where I can grow technically and professionally. Passionate about building servers, libraries, frameworks, and tools with Go for the cloud.

Technical Skills

Languages: *Advanced:* Go, Python, Java, JavaScript, SQL, C, *Proficient:* Node.js, Ruby, PHP, C#, Bash, HTML, CSS, *Past Experience:* C++, Haskell, Scheme

Back end: *Advanced:* Kubernetes, Docker, MySQL, PostgresQL, Cassandra, Helm, gRPC, HTTP, REST, *Proficient:* AWS, Kafka, InfluxDB, GraphQL, Kapacitor, *Past Experience:* GCP, Rails, Terraform, Spinnaker, Grafana, Graphite, Kibana, CircleCI, Travis CI, Jenkins, Drone, Vagrant, Skaffold, Express, Hapi

Front end: Past Experience: AngularJS, Lodash, Underscore.js, Q, Mocha, Jade, WebDriver

Tools: *Advanced:* Git, GitHub, Make, Linux, Mac, *Proficient:* Windows, *Past Experience:* Docker Compose, Docker Machine, GitLab, Bazel

Professional Experience

UJET — San Francisco, California

Senior Software Engineer — August 2020 – December 2020

- Member of a team that built features for analyzing and reporting call and chat data for a customer support communication platform that spanned phones, apps, and websites.
- Designed, built, and tested Ruby on Rails models and services that queried and processed call and chat data for a new dashboard feature that enabled supervisors to review agent productivity.
- Implemented and measured a proposed fix for ElastiCache processor spikes during deployment. Investigated the performance, and identified the largest performance hit.
- Completed three AWS training courses: Developing on AWS, Advanced Developing on AWS, and Running Container-Enabled Microservices on AWS.
- Tech: Ruby, Rails, MySQL, AWS, SQL, Bash, Git, GitHub, HTTP, Linux, Mac, REST

Turntide — San Francisco, California

Senior Software Engineer — August 2019 – April 2020

- Member of a team that built cloud infrastructure and microservices for ingesting, processing, storing, and accessing IoT telemetry and information for electric motors and related field devices.
- Designed and built the company's first public API to provide customers access to thousands of raw telemetry data points for hundreds of IoT devices. Created REST HTTP handlers and middleware, PostgresQL and InfluxDB queries, and an OAuth2 scheme for our Auth0 tenants. Migrated SQL databases. Split feature designs into rollout phases. It was the team's first path to potential revenue.
- Contributed to an alerting system for IoT device faults and connectivity problems. Created a gRPC service and exposed it with GraphQL loaders and resolvers. Enriched alerts with problem details.
- Tech: Go, Python, Kubernetes, Kafka, InfluxDB, PostgresQL, AWS, SQL, Bash, Bazel, Docker, Drone, Git, GitHub, GitLab, Grafana, GraphQL, gRPC, HTTP, Helm, Kapacitor, Linux, Mac, REST, Skaffold

Mercari — Palo Alto, California

Senior Software Engineer — August 2017 – November 2018

- Member of a team that built microservices for the API of an online marketplace for secondhand items. Designed, implemented, tested, and deployed features and fixes across the board.
- Built a microservice that tracked user statistics and awarded user profile badges to gamify and encourage user behavior like fast, reliable shipping and quick messaging.
- Built buyer subscriptions for interests like brands and sellers, and then built a home screen item feed using subscription information to improve relevance for buyers and drive higher engagement.
- Designed the engineering job interview process. Interviewed candidates by phone and in person.
- Wrote the team's Go code standard and documented team processes and procedures.
- Tech: Go, PHP, Kubernetes, MySQL, gRPC, GCP, SQL, Bash, CircleCI, Docker, Drone, Git, GitHub, Grafana, HTTP, Kibana, Linux, Mac, Spinnaker

BigCommerce — San Francisco, California Senior Software Engineer — September 2016 – June 2017

- Member of a team that built microservices for a template engine for customized e-commerce website front ends. Designed, implemented, tested, and deployed features and fixes across the board.
- Prototyped a Go system of loosely-coupled component interfaces that enabled transparent network connections between them and flexible implementations behind the interfaces, such as splitting interface implementations into separate decoration layers for transports, logging, and metrics.
- Designed a public REST API that uses JSON over HTTP for a new store theme system.
- Built a library for graceful HTTP and gRPC stops and restarts for Go servers.
- Wrote the company's Go code standard, slides for teaching Go, and a compilation of Go resources.
- Tech: Go, Node.js, Ruby, PHP, Rails, Bash, Docker, Git, GitHub, gRPC, Hapi, HTTP, Linux, Mac

Betable — San Francisco, California

Senior Software Engineer — May 2014 – March 2016

- Member of a team that built microservices and a web app for communicating with and marketing to customers. Designed, implemented, tested, and deployed features and fixes across the board.
- Promoted from Software Engineer to Senior Software Engineer after about a year.
- Refactored the communication service to manage scheduled tasks with a separate cron service using resilient chains of asynchronous jobs that invoked webhooks in the communication server.
- Prototyped a Go RPC framework that split code into separate layers like logging and metrics.
- Prototyped a Go ORM framework that enabled safe database backfills, migrations, and rollbacks.
- Built a mockable Cassandra client and a Cassandra Query Language generator library.
- Spearheaded upgrading Cassandra to 2.0. Presented it to the team and convinced them.
- Wrote the company's Go code standard and Go and Node.js ramp-up guides for new hires.
- Won a company hackathon for adding live chat customer support to the website.
- Tech: Go, Node.js, MySQL, Cassandra, SQL, AngularJS, Bash, CSS, Express, Git, GitHub, HTML, HTTP, Jade, JavaScript, Kibana, Linux, Lodash, Mac, Mocha, Q, Underscore.js

VMware/Hillview Technologies — Mountain View, California Software Engineer — April 2013 – April 2014

- Member of a team that built a web proxy that rendered pages remotely and displayed them locally without needing special local software. Built tests, benchmarks, and supporting infrastructure.
- Measured and tracked page load performance in various scenarios to identify regressions.
- Built a monitor for the web proxy that reported critical situations and restarted troubled processes.
- Overhauled the test framework. Simplified many tests by adding various helper methods.
- Implemented Git commit hooks. Configured an LDAP server and other services to use it. Wrote a Kickstart file for the servers. Updated the public website. Built a tool that provisioned test VMs.

• Tech: **Python, JavaScript, MySQL, SQL,** Bash, Chrome, Git, HTML, Jenkins, LDAP, Linux, Mac, Red Hat Enterprise Linux, vCenter, vSphere, WebDriver

Microsoft — Redmond, Washington

Software Engineer — November 2008 – June 2011

- Implemented the ToggleSwitch and Navigation UI controls for Silverlight on Windows 8.
- Contributed to the Windows Phone Toolkit collection of UI controls for Silverlight:
 - Designed, implemented, and tested a library of 27 control transition animations.
 - Built the WrapPanel, ToggleSwitch, and AutoCompleteBox controls.
 - Supported customers via blogging, bug reports, code samples, and an on-site visit.
- Investigated functional and compatibility defects and performance regressions and implemented fixes for Windows Presentation Foundation and Extensible Application Markup Language.
- Tech: C#, C++, Silverlight, WPF, Team Foundation Server, Visual Studio, Windows, XAML

Apple — Cupertino, California

Software Engineer Intern — June 2007 – September 2007

- Designed and built a scalable test template tool with Java for the iTunes Store content team.
- Converted existing test templates for the new tool with Python and XML.
- Presented the new tool to the senior vice president.

Telestream — Nevada City, California

Software Engineer Intern — June 2006 – September 2006

- Designed, implemented, and tested a standalone configuration upgrade tool with C++ and XML.
- Implemented features for blurring, outlining, and wrapping text in transcoded video with C++.
- Discovered software requirements through independent investigation.

RSA Security — San Mateo, California

Software Test Engineer Intern — June 2005 – September 2005

- Instrumented the test infrastructure to measure the impact of several variables on throughput.
- Tabulated and compared the performance measurements with Python, Bash, HTML, and CSS.
- Presented the data and the optimal virtual machine configuration to the team.

Data Control — Roseville, California

Software Test Engineer Intern — June 2003 – September 2003

- Prepared acceptance criteria and test cases for application releases occurring every two weeks.
- Tested features and defect fixes with functional, regression, and ad hoc testing.

Education & Achievements

- Bachelor of Science and Master of Science in Computer Science from California Polytechnic State University, San Luis Obispo, California
- Master's thesis: *Interoperation for Lazy and Eager Evaluation*. Presented a method of transparent interoperation for functional languages having incompatible evaluation strategies.
- Eagle Scout, Boy Scouts of America